-Ken went to Tokyo. -Tokyo?
-研先生好像跑去東京了 -東京？
He told Amakusa that he wanted to go on the radio.
他好像對天草先生說 他想要上廣播節目
It's almost three o'clock.
馬上就要到三點了
Let's call SNACK MAN. Where is he today?
來呼叫點心男吧，他今天在哪裡呢？
Hello. I am here. I am Junpei Amakusa.
好的，我就在這裡，我是天草純平
It's time for you and I
你和我的時間，我和你的進化論
If you are worried about something
有煩惱就問天草
Ask Amakusa
去問問天草吧
In response to Tokachi and Ririe's request,
為了回應十勝先生 跟莉莉惠小姐的要求
I brought him here today.
今天我把人帶來這裡了
This is Frankenstein.
這位就是科學怪人先生
You must be joking.
不會吧？
Are you Frankenstein?
你…就是科學怪人先生？
Yes. I am Frankenstein. I am 120 years old.
是的，我就是科學怪人，120歲
Ken is now on the radio.
研先生上節目了呢，出現了
-Wow. -It's starting.
-哇 -出現了啊？
-Is this the place called radio? -Finally.
-這裡就是廣播嗎？ -終於啊
Yes, this is a studio in the radio station.
對啊，這裡就是廣播局的錄音室
You are so cool.
好帥
Frankenstein, you are good-looking.
科學怪人先生還真帥啊
I'm obsessed with him.
這女人愛上研先生了
He is good-looking, isn't he?
對吧，莉莉惠？他是個帥哥呢
Come and sit next to me.
來，坐這裡
So, what are you going to do in here?
那麼…今天你是來做什麼的？
Hey, you asked him to come.
等等…明明是十勝先生你找他來的
Not me, you did.
明明就是你
Ask him anything.
今天請盡量問吧
If you are worried about something,
-有煩惱也能跟科學怪人先生說 -這樣啊
Do you want us to tell him what we are worried about?
我們跟科學怪人先生商量煩惱？
Yes.
是的
-Ask Frankenstein -Ask Frankenstein…
去問問科學怪人先生吧 他是為此而來的
Franken… It's a long name.
去問問科學怪人…字還真多啊
-Can I call you Franken? -OK.
那個，我可以直接 叫你科學怪人先生嗎？
I want to ask you something.
我其實正因為 科學怪人先生你而煩惱呢
Are you mad at me, Franken?
科學怪人先生你…生我的氣嗎？
No, I'm not.
不…我沒生氣
I said that you should kill yourself
因為我說了，若你是會殺人的怪物
if you think that you are a monster who will kill someone.
就自己去死吧
First of all, why did you say that you may kill someone?
那個…說來說去 為何你覺得自己可能會殺人？
Because I am weak.
那是因為…我很軟弱
Weak?
-軟弱？ -對
I understand. Sometimes I want to kill Tokachi.
我懂，我偶爾也會想把十勝先生殺掉
Why?
什麼啊？
-I have no confidence in myself either. -That's because you're mad at me.
-我很不安呢 -你只是在生氣而已
What kind of person do you think you are?
科學怪人先生覺得自己 是怎麼樣的人呢？
-What kind of person? -Yes.
-怎麼樣的人？ -嗯
I am not human.
我…不是人類
I was born in a deep forest.
我…是在深山森林裡誕生的
Stop it, Ken.
別說了，研先生
I died once.
我…曾經死過一次
My father was a doctor of medicine.
而身為醫學博士的父親 是在120年前
He raised me from the dead 120 years ago.
讓我死而復生的
What is Ken talking about?
研先生…到底在胡說什麼啊？
He is joking, but it's not fun.
不妙，完全冷場了
OK.
嗯
-You can go now. Thank you. -Then what happened?
回去吧，我懂了，回去吧
I left the forest after I met someone.
我遇上了某個人，因此離開了森林
Did you fall in love with a human?
你愛上了人類吧？
-Yes. -You can go now.
-是的 -門口就在那邊
What kind of person is she? You said that she was very sick.
對方是怎樣的人？ 是患有重病的人嗎？
Yes.
是的
She is sick but very strong.
但是…她也是非常堅強的人
She is strong and kind.
她是個堅強又溫柔的人
I am the opposite.
我…跟她剛好相反
So, I want to be strong and kind like her.
所以我想成為像她一樣 堅強又溫柔的人
But I can't.
但是，我還很不習慣
I didn't know anything about humans. I didn't understand anything.
我對人類還一無所知，什麼都不懂
Although I am 100 years older than her…
明明我就比她多活了一百年
I know nothing.
卻什麼也不懂
So, I want to ask people who are listening to the radio.
所以，各位廣播聽眾們，請告訴我
How can I learn about humans?
我該怎麼做才能了解人類呢？
How can I be strong?
要怎麼做才能變得更堅強呢？
Humans can change by thinking about what to do.
人會因煩惱而改變
Amakusa told me so.
這是天草先生告訴我的
I am worried about whether I can protect her or not.
我的煩惱就是守護她的這件事
I want to live with her in the human world.
和她一起在人類世界活下去的這件事
So, I need to know more about humans.
為此，我必須更了解人類才行
I want to change more.
我想更加地改變
Dear listeners.
就是這樣，各位聽眾
Please tell Frankenstein how he can be more human.
請告訴我們科學怪人該怎麼做 才能變得更像人類呢？
See you tomorrow.
那麼明天再見了
If you are worrying about something during snack time…
下午三點，點心時間的煩惱
Ask Amakusa
就交給天草吧
Ken doesn't know who he is.
研先生因為不懂自己而非常煩惱呢
I wish he could get his memory back.
要是他能想起過去的記憶就好了
How can he recover from memory loss?
喪失記憶要怎麼治好啊？
How about giving him a terrible shock?
遇到強大的衝擊？
Like getting lightning strikes or slipping?
或是被閃電擊中？或是笑話冷場？
He slipped and fell, but he was all right.
他肯定很習慣冷場了啦
But not everyone has a happy past.
但是，他的過去 也不一定就比較幸福啊
Who are you?
你誰啊？
-Thank you.
-辛苦了
Thank you. It was really good.
辛苦了，太好了
Amakusa.
天草
Is this what you want?
你真的認為可以這樣嗎？
I don't know why you brought this man here.
雖然我不知道你這是從哪找來的人
-Why are you sticking to this topic? -Don't get too excited.
-但你要搞這個爛梗到何時？ -算了啦
Actually, you are sticking to this topic, Tokachi.
恕我直言 一直搞爛梗的是十勝先生你們
It doesn't matter.
就算了吧，又沒關係
We've brought it to an end, anyway.
這樣起碼有個高潮
I don't think so.
哪裡高潮了啊？
He made my radio show confused.
只是讓我的節目變得莫名其妙而已
Amakusa. Do you really think that this is fun?
天草，你真的覺得這有趣嗎？
It is the listeners who decide if it is fun.
不…有不有趣應該由聽眾來決定吧？
-What did you say? -It was OK.
-你說什麼？ -好了啦
Let's wait for the listeners' response.
就用聽眾的反應來決定吧
Let's take a picture and post it on the website.
那大家一起拍張合照吧 可以放上網站
I think Franken is good-looking.
科學怪人先生的外型 應該會蠻受歡迎的
-Do you think so? -Let me take a picture.
-是嗎？ -我也正打算拍張照
Please look here and smile.
大家請看這裡，露出微笑
Ken, look over there.
研先生，看那邊
OK? Say cheese.
我要拍囉，笑一個
Thank you.
好的，拍好囉
He is very smart.
他的頭腦相當好呢
He knows how the radio works.
完全掌握了廣播的特性
He talked on the radio, not because he couldn't lie
他不是不會說謊
but because he knew that he didn't have to lie.
而是早就判斷出 就算說實話也沒關係
Do you think he acted as he planned?
您是說這都是他算計過的嗎？
He's got a high social adaptability in such a short time
在這麼短的時間內 他的社會適應力可說是相當高
because he realized that he loved someone.
正是因為感受到對別人的愛 更提高了他的適應力
Do you think he can live as a normal human this way?
照這情況 他能以普通人類的身份生活嗎？
I don't know.
這就不得而知了
The risk is getting higher.
相對地，風險也會變高
He releases bacteria when he gets excited.
他會因感情高漲而釋放菌類
As he gets more complex emotions,
今後他的情感越是複雜
we never know when and how he will release bacteria.
越是不知道他會在何時 釋放出怎樣的菌類
Hi, Ken.
深志先生
-Welcome back. -I'm back.
-歡迎回來 -我回來了
Did you come back by yourself?
你自己一個人回來的嗎？
Amakusa told me how to.
是天草先生教我的
-Let's go home. -Yes.
-那就回去吧 -好的
Did you have fun?
開心嗎？
Yes, I did.
是的，非常開心
Why did you want to go on the radio?
為什麼會想去上廣播節目呢？
Because I want to know more about Tsugumi.
因為我想更加了解津輕小姐
I have to learn more about humans.
為此，我必須更加了解 關於人類的事
Did someone tell you to do that?
是有人跟你這麼說的嗎？
No. I want to do it.
不，這是我的願望
I didn't understand what you said on the radio,
雖然是個莫名其妙的廣播節目
but I'm glad you did well. Cheers.
但恭喜你在廣播界出道囉 來，乾杯吧
-Cheers.
-乾杯
Thank you very much.
謝謝大家
But why did you make up that character?
但是，研啊
Frankenstein, who was raised from the dead.
從屍體復活的科學怪人
It's the same character as His Excellency Demon.
跟小暮閣下是同一路線啊
Ken Fukashi and Franken sound similar.
話說回來，深志研這個名字 跟科學怪人發音很像啊
That's why I named him Frankenstein as a nickname.
所以我才會幫他取 “科學怪人”這個化名啊
-I see. -That's just like you.
-原來如此 -不愧是少爺
That's how he played that character.
所以才會有那樣的角色設定啊？
What did you think, Tsugumi?
津輕小姐覺得如何？
He confessed his love to you on the radio.
在廣播節目被告白的感覺
"I left the forest because I fell in love with a human."
我…愛上人類，離開了森林
-Are you mimicking Ken? -Yes.
-居然在模仿研先生啊？ -是的
He is annoying.
真麻煩
"I can't be human."
我沒辦法成為人類
-Are you mimicking Tetsuya? -"I am 100 years older than her,
那是在學鐵矢吧？
-But I love her." -Nice.
但是，我還是喜歡她
Shut up. You just like dirty jokes.
吵耶，別發出渴求黃色笑話的 噁心男的聲音
Don't talk to me like that.
你這是什麼話啊？什麼噁心男？
But you are right, Mikoto.
但是或許正像美琴所說
Tsugumi may be worried about something.
津輕小姐也有辛苦的一面
Ken wants to cheer her up. Don't make fun of them.
研先生明明就只是想幫她加油打氣
You should be careful.
你有什麼資格講這些啊？
Don't worry. I'm fine, as you can see.
沒關係的，如各位所見，我很有精神
Please don't worry about me.
請不要擔心我
I will protect Tsugumi.
津輕小姐…就由我來守護
-Oh!
-哦！
-Shut up!
-吵死了！
-You guys are so noisy. -Let's drink.
-你們真的很吵耶 -快喝吧
Let me bring it here.
-我去拿 -拿最好的來
PARADISE HEAVEN
（樂園天國）
ASK AMAKUSA
（問問天草吧）
How long will they continue this topic for?
這話題會持續到何時？
I don't know.
不知道
If the listeners don't like it, they will delete this picture soon.
若毫無迴響的話 這張照片應該早就被刪掉了
Excuse me.
抱歉，我接個電話
Hey, look at this.
真是的
-Ouch… -It looks so bad.
-好了… -怎麼這樣學人家啊？
Hello.
你好
-How was he? -I didn't see anything strange.
-怎麼樣了？ -沒什麼異狀啊
Why did you say that he was dangerous?
他哪裡危險了？
He is not dangerous if you don't make him mad.
只要不惹他生氣就沒事
It's OK if he doesn't get too excited.
只要不讓他異常地情緒高漲就好
Do you still want him to go on your radio program?
比起這個，還要繼續讓他上廣播嗎？
I can't just quit. We got great feedback.
這樣下去是沒辦法停下來的 迴響太大了
Is Ken popular?
研先生那麼有人氣啊…
It's interesting.
還真是有趣呢
Is he around? Can I talk to Ken?
那個，如果研先生就在你附近 能換他來聽嗎？
OK.
我知道了
Ken.
研先生
-Mr. Amakusa wants to talk to you. -Mr. Amakusa?
-天草先生想跟你說話 -天草先生？
You can talk to him now.
用這個就能說了
TOKYO MUSASHI BROADCASTING MR. AMAKUSA
（東京武藏廣播局 天草先生）
He's here.
請
Hi. This is Amakusa.
你好，我是天草
Hi. This is Ken Fukashi.
是的，我是深志研
Ken.
研先生
Everyone is rooting for you.
大家都在為你加油呢
-Rooting for me? -Yes.
-加油？ -沒錯
Many people think that they are not human, just like you.
也就是說有很多人 也覺得自己不是人類
They feel empathy for you as you want to know about humans.
那些人對於研先生你 想更了解人類的煩惱起了共鳴
Will you read their messages on the radio?
能請研先生你 在錄音室幫這些人聽聽煩惱嗎？
Hi. This is Tsugumi.
你好，我是津輕
Good evening, Ms. Tsugaru.
津輕小姐，你好
Do you want Ken to go on the radio again?
又要找深志先生去上廣播了嗎？
Ken made this happen.
這是研先生自己走出的道路
The listeners want to see how Ken's love will go.
聽眾們都想守護研先生 和津輕小姐的戀情
Ken made contact with society through the radio.
研先生透過廣播 證明了自己是跟社會有關連的
It was good for you.
真的是可喜可賀
OK.
我明白了
I will go on the radio again.
我會再去上廣播節目的
Great. I will be preparing for it.
太好了，那我們這邊準備好以後
I will call you again.
再連絡你
OK.
好的
I heard that Franken is becoming very popular.
看來怪人的人氣很驚人呢
Popular?
人氣？
People saw his picture on the website
很多聽眾都說看了網站上的照片
and said that he didn't look like a 120-year-old man.
完全看不出來他有120歲
I can imagine that.
信以為真的人才奇怪吧？
A project to cheer him up is about to launch
甚至還有人
to help him adjust to the human world.
要組成幫助他在人類世界 活下去的支援計畫
What is that project?
什麼支援計畫啊？
-They are kind, like me. -You doubted him first.
-大家都跟我一樣，很溫柔的 -你原本還懷疑根本沒這個人呢
But I met him.
但我已經看到他本人啦
-It's almost three o'clock. -Are you going to introduce him?
-馬上就要三點了 -何時輪到你說了？
-I wonder where Amakusa is today. -Go on.
-天草先生今天會在哪裡呢？ -夠了，快叫他吧
Let me call SNACK MAN, Amakusa!
好的，點心男，天草先生
It's between mystery and everyday life
不可思議與日常生活之間 相遇與別離的理型論
If you are worried about something
迷惘的人就去找天草
ASK AMAKUSA
（問問天草吧）
Ask Amakusa
去問問天草吧
Hello. I am Junpei Amakusa.
好的，我是天草純平
It was the second verse of the Amakusa song.
剛才是天草之歌二號
Today we have a guest here.
就是這樣，今天這位也來了
It is Frankenstein.
是的，就是科學怪人先生
Hi. I am Frankenstein.
好的，我就是科學怪人
Here is a message to Franken.
馬上就來看看 聽眾寄給科學怪人的訊息吧
It's from "Kramer vs. Kramer", 21 years old, Tokyo.
這位是東京都 抱怨抱怨小姐，21歲
-"Hi, Franken." -Hello.
-“科學怪人先生，初次見面” -初次見面
"I heard you talk on the radio.
“我在廣播裡聽到 科學怪人先生說的話
I understand that you said you were not human yet.
覺得自己還不算人類的心情 我很明白
I recommend you to work at a convenience store
如果想更理解人類 我推薦你去超商工作
I am working at a convenience store.
我就在超商工作
People don't treat shop assistants at convenience stores as humans."
常常覺得超商店員 根本不被當成人看待”
So, I came to the convenience store where she works.
所以，我們來到了超商
MONMART
（超商）
Hi. Are you "Kramer vs. Kramer", who sent us a message?
你就是投稿的抱怨抱怨小姐嗎？
Yes.
是的，就是我
Here is Franken.
我帶了怪人來了呢
-Nice to meet you.
-初次見面
-What do you think? -I think he is good-looking.
-感覺如何？ -這…他真的很帥呢
I see.
很帥吧？
Franken will work with you today.
今天會請怪人也一起工作
We got permission from your manager. Will you teach him what to do?
已經獲得店家同意了 事不宜遲，請教他怎麼工作吧
-OK. -Thank you.
-好的，我明白了 -請多指教
You are very welcome.
我才是，請多指教
-Come inside, Franken. -OK.
-那麼，怪人，進去吧 -好的
Come with me.
請進
Let me get back to you and Ririe while we wait for them to get ready.
十勝先生，莉莉惠小姐 準備完成前先把節目交給你們
What's going on? Don't get back to us.
這是怎麼回事？突然就交給我們了
I'm excited to see what they will do.
是啊，很期待會發生什麼事呢
What if nothing happens? They are just doing a part-time job.
要是什麼都沒發生該怎麼辦啊？ 根本只是直播打工而已
It's OK. Please listen to this song while we are waiting.
好了啦
Why is Ken goofing off and doing another job?
研這傢伙 為何翹班跑去做其他工作啊？
He is trying to get a lot of experience in life.
這個嘛，增加人生經驗囉
I wonder what Amakusa wants to do.
天草先生到底想做什麼呢？
I don't know.
天知道…
I hope that Ken won't panic.
只要他別引起混亂就好了
But it would not be fun as a radio program.
但這樣以節目來說就不有趣了吧
Hello.
歡迎光臨
Hi, Tokachi and Ririe. This is Amakusa.
十勝先生、莉莉惠小姐，都準備好囉
Franken is working hard.
怪人工作的樣子很不錯呢
He is the customer who throws money.
這好像就是會扔錢的客人
Hello.
歡迎光臨
Franken is scanning the barcode.
怪人馬上開始打收銀機了
He is a fast learner.
學得還真快呢
Please ask if he wants to warm up the bento box.
請問問客人便當是否要加熱
Would you like it warmed up?
請問便當要加熱嗎？
Oops.
這…
He is wearing headphones.
面對帶著耳機的客人
He can't hear what Franken says.
怪人的聲音似乎沒傳達出去
Would you like it warmed up?
客人…便當要加熱嗎？
He said yes.
好像要加熱呢
-OK. Please ring up the item first. -OK.
-好的，那請你先結帳吧 -好的
This is the second biggest hurdle. Ring up the item.
第二難關，收錢
767 yen in total, please.
總共是767元
767 yen. What will he do?
767元，客人會怎麼做呢？
He takes a 1,000 yen bill and… he throws money.
拿出了千元鈔票，扔了出去
He throws money as if he is making a money offering.
就像丟香油錢一樣 客人把錢扔到桌上
You have paid 1,000 yen…
收您一千元
233 yen…
233元…
Here is your change.
這是找您的錢
Franken throws money, too.
把零錢丟到桌上了，怪人也扔錢了
Hey. What are you doing?
喂，你對客人這是什麼態度？
-The customer is getting mad. -Why are you throwing money?
-客人生氣了 -為何用丟的？
No wonder he gets mad.
客人有點生氣，這也難怪
I thought you wanted me to throw money back to you.
我以為客人您喜歡用丟的
What the hell?!
什麼鬼？
-Where is my bento box? -It's in the microwave.
-便當呢？ -正在加熱
I didn't ask you to heat it up.
加什麼熱啊？不准擅自決定！
-You didn't want this? -He is so mad.
-您不想要加熱嗎？ -完全抓狂了
You nodded your head when I asked you.
因為剛才問客人您 是否要加熱，您點頭了
No, I didn't. I don't want to heat it up.
我才沒點頭呢，憑什麼擅自加熱啊？
I want my bento box at my favorite temperature.
我有我自己喜歡的便當溫度
-Let me get a new one. -Are you sure?
-我馬上幫您換一個 -這是你說的喔
This is the last one. Go to the factory and get a new one.
這便當只剩一個，你給我去工廠拿
He is a typical complainer.
這個客人似乎是典型的奧客
I am very sorry.
非常抱歉
She went to the shelf to get a new one, but there is none.
店員要狂奔去找便當了 雖然找了，但都沒剩了
Hey. Listen.
說來說去…
You didn't ask me if I wanted to heat it up.
你根本沒問我要不要加熱
-I did. -No, you didn't.
-我問了 -你才沒問
Well?
嗯？
-What is this? -Franken picked up his headphones
-這是什麼？ -此時怪人把對方的耳機拿了下來
and put them on his head.
放到自己耳朵上…
It's too noisy.
太大聲了，耳朵…
No wonder you can't hear anything.
客人，這樣什麼也聽不到
He can't hear.
當然聽不到了
Don't touch my headphones.
你在胡鬧什麼？
Hey!
喂！
What happened?
-發生什麼事了？ -不知道
Huh?
啊？
I am very sorry.
不好意思
I didn't know
我不知道對客人您來說
that the temperature of your bento box is very important to you.
便當的溫度居然這麼重要
Thank you for teaching me that.
謝謝您願意告訴我
Shut up.
給我閉嘴
-Are you making fun of me? -No.
-竟敢瞧不起我？ -沒這回事
I appreciate it.
真是太好了
Thank you for teaching me that.
謝謝您告訴我
The customer is getting quiet.
客人好像突然安份了下來
It seems that Franken had settled the situation peacefully.
看來怪人成功打了圓場
Darn it.
別開玩笑了！
-Thank you very much.
-謝謝光臨
See you tomorrow.
那麼明天再見了，點心時間的煩惱
Ask Amakusa
就交給天草吧
It wasn't fun.
什麼啊，真無聊
What?
什麼？
I mean as a radio program.
我是說以廣播來說
What? Did you say that you may extend his program?
什麼？今後可能還會延長時間？ 什麼意思？
Do you want to extend Amakusa's program?
是要擴大天草的單元嗎？
I will let him do as he wants regarding Franken.
要是怪人的這個梗能繼續用下去 我打算讓他們自行發揮
Please cheer him up.
你也幫他們炒熱氣氛啊
I don't understand what he wants to do.
不…我不懂這到底是想做什麼
Do you really think that it was fun?
湯河原先生，你真的覺得這有趣嗎？
ASK AMAKUSA!
（問問天草吧）
It's not up to me to decide if it's fun or not.
到底有不有趣，不是我能決定的
I am counting on you.
拜託囉
It's a time for you and I
你和我的時間，我和你的進化論
If you are worried about something
有煩惱就問天草
Ask Amakusa
去問問天草吧
Hi. I am Junpei Amakusa.
好的，我是天草純平
Hi. I am Frankenstein.
好的，我是科學怪人
Here is a message.
今天收到這樣的訊息
It's from "Sora Beans", 37 years old, Kanagawa.
來自神奈川縣的蠶豆小姐，37歲
"The best way to know about humans is to attend divorce mediation.
“怪人先生，想了解人類
You will never want to do something foolish as to love humans."
你就不會想做出愛上人類 這種愚蠢的舉動了”
I see.
就是這樣
What a message!
好驚人的訊息呢
I can't believe it.
是的，很難相信呢
Let's go listen to divorce mediation.
那麼就趕快去聽聽 協調離婚的人是怎麼說的吧
AOYAMA ICHIBANKAN
（青山一番館）
Hi. This is Amakusa.
午安，敝姓天草
Are you the "Sora Beans" who wrote to us?
-您就是投稿的蠶豆小姐吧？ -是的
I am a big fan of yours.
我是你的粉絲
-What's this? -This is a radio program.
-這是幹嘛？ -不好意思，我們是廣播節目
Radio?
廣播節目？
You are on the radio, so watch your mouth.
現在正在直播，說話小心點
Are you kidding me?
開什麼玩笑啊？
Sorry to disturb you. My name is Junpei Amakusa.
打擾了，我是天草純平
I'm Frankenstein.
我是科學怪人
-Who? -He is a monster
-誰啊？ -就是怪物啊
and he wants to know about human nature, right?
想了解人類本性的怪物，對吧？
Give me a break.
真受不了
Do you want to ask them any questions?
怪人，你有什麼想問兩位的嗎？
Did you get married because you fell in love?
兩位是愛上對方，所以才結婚的吧？
Right. And the love was over when we got married.
沒錯，但結婚後愛情就結束了
He started getting other girlfriends.
然後這男人就開始跟別人談戀愛了
Other girlfriends?
跟別人談戀愛？
He cheated on me so many times and treated me like a doormat.
一直在外面找女人 完全無視於我的存在
No, I didn't.
我沒無視你啊
I treated you well by drawing the line between you and them.
我是我，你是你 我也是一直很珍惜你的啊
Drawing the line? Do you know what he's saying?
我是我，你是你？ 你懂他在說什麼嗎？
-Not really. -See?
-不太明白 -對吧？
Every time I found him cheating on me,
也就是說，我每次跟他吵外遇的事
he said that he didn't care if we got divorced
他就擺出隨時可以離婚的態度
and continued to have an affair. Then, did you see what happened?
一直重覆同樣的行為，然後是怎樣？
I fell in love with another man and told him that I wanted to leave him.
等我愛上別人，說可以跟他離婚時
Then he said that he never wanted to divorce me.
他卻說絕對不跟我離婚
He says I betrayed him and he doesn't want to get divorced.
說我背叛他，居然不願意跟我離婚
-Men and women are different. -How?
-男人跟女人的立場不同啊 -哪裡不同了？
Do you think I have no right to have an affair because you make a living?
你是想說靠你的錢生活的我 就連外遇的權利也沒有嗎？
In short, that's right.
-說極端一點就是這樣 -出現了
He wants to change my sense of value on his own circumstances.
結果都只是為了自己 而改變對方的價值，你懂嗎？
-A little. -Who do you think is right?
-好像有點懂 -你懂誰的部分？
I don't know.
我都不太清楚
But I can understand that both of you are sad.
我只知道兩位都很傷心
-Sad? -Yes.
-傷心？ -是的
Both of you fell in love with someone else,
因為，明明愛上了別人
but neither of you look happy.
看起來卻一點也不開心
I am sad because he doesn't agree to our divorce.
那是因為這男人不跟我離婚 我才會傷心啊
The nature of love is sadness, not happiness?
戀愛的真相不是開心，而是悲傷嗎？
Right. That's love.
沒錯，到頭來戀愛就是這樣
-I am sad, too. -Franken.
-我也很悲傷 -怪人
This is not what we call feeling sad. We feel empty.
這與其說是悲傷，不如說是空虛
What's the difference between feeling sad and empty?
悲傷跟空虛差在哪裡？
You feel sad when someone you trust betrays you.
被相信的人背叛是悲傷
You feel empty when someone is not trustworthy.
但從一開始就不值得相信的就是空虛
ASK AMAKUSA
（問問天草吧）
This man fell in love, got married, had an affair,
這位男性的生活方式 無論是戀愛、結婚或外遇
but all he did was to make someone feel empty.
都只會讓人感到空虛而已
There is a man like that.
但這也只是代表 世界上也有這種人而已
Right?
對吧？
Shut up.
少囉嗦！
I will divorce you.
我這就跟你離婚
Amakusa, are you all right?
天草先生，你沒事吧？
Yes.
-沒事 -那個…
Yes! Thank you very much.
太好了！謝謝你
-You're welcome. -Yes! Thank you very much.
-是的 -太好了，謝謝
See you tomorrow.
那麼…明天再見囉
If you are worried about something during snack time…
下午三點，點心時間，有煩惱就…
Ask Amakusa
去問問天草吧
-Get it done by today. -OK.
-今天內要做好 -好
Did you finish that?
再一次吧
-How is it? -It's fine.
-怎麼樣？ -沒問題
-Let's finish it up later. -Okay, okay.
-待會我還可以做一下
OK.
好的
-It's good. -Okay.
-很好 -好
-Hello. -Hi, Seiya.
-你好 -稻庭先生
-Nothing happened. -Mr. Amakusa.
-根本什麼也沒發生啊 -天草先生
Are you trying to cause trouble on purpose?
你是故意要引發意外的嗎？
Yes. That's what you want.
這不就是稻庭先生你的期望嗎？
What should I do next?
接下來該怎麼做？
I can't be responsible for what will happen.
不管怎樣都跟我無關
Seiya.
學長
Hello.
午安
-Did you listen to the radio? -Yes.
-你有聽廣播了嗎？ -嗯
I was worried about him.
又讓我有點緊張了
Me, too.
我也是
What time will he come back?
是幾點呢？
I will go pick him up by 6:30 p.m.
應該是六點半會到
INANIWA CORPORATION
（稻庭建築公司）
FRANKEN
（科學怪人好帥）
Hi, Tsugumi.
-津輕小姐 -是
-I'm back. -Welcome back.
-我回來了 -歡迎回來
Ken, you are becoming popular.
研先生的人氣上漲不少呢
Popular?
人氣是什麼？
You connect to a lot of people.
就是你和越來越多人產生連結了
Are you having a hard time?
你不覺得痛苦嗎？
No.
是的，我不覺得痛苦
I learn about humans from the radio.
廣播教會我更多關於人類的事
I want to know more about humans
我會更加瞭解人類
and protect you.
好好守護津輕小姐
INANIWA CORPORATION
（稻庭建築公司）
Hey, Ken.
研
You don't want to work with us anymore, do you?
你不打算跟我們一起工作了嗎？
Hey! Calm down.
穴食，冷靜點
Yes, I do.
沒這回事
Then work properly.
那就認真工作
But your radio program is interesting. I like it.
但是研先生的廣播很有趣，我很喜歡
-Thank you. -He is right.
-謝謝 -就是說啊
People like your character. You play it longer than I thought.
我還以為大家馬上就會膩
You never know what you will be.
或許還會再進化呢
Demon became a sumo commentator from a wax figure.
小暮閣下也是從蠟像 變成相撲評論家的
I can learn more by going on the radio than listening to it.
比起聽廣播 直接上廣播能了解更多事
Don't get carried away!
別得意忘形了
It's for Tsugumi, right?
這也是為了津輕小姐嘛
Yes.
是的
Don't take it wrong.
別會錯意了
You are a carpenter, not an entertainer.
你可是木工職人，不是什麼藝人
Ken decides what to do.
研先生有他的自由
No one can tell him how to live.
沒人能決定他一定要怎麼過活
-Don't take it the wrong way. -Calm down.
-你這樣才是會錯意 -別說了啦
We have no right to keep him in a small place.
我們沒有權力
-Let's drink. -OK.
-快喝吧 -快喝
This is delicious.
-超好喝的 -真好喝
Have you ever thought that you feel empty?
津輕小姐
-Feel empty? -Yes.
-空虛？ -對
I'm trying not to feel that way.
我盡量不讓自己這樣想
Why?
不讓自己這樣想？
My father got remarried after my mother died
我的父親在母親過世後
and had another family.
另組了家庭
What do you mean?
那是怎麼一回事？
Did you feel empty or sad?
那是空虛嗎？還是悲傷呢？
I didn't feel empty or sad.
我不覺得空虛，也不覺得悲傷
I'm glad that my father was happy.
我父親能獲得幸福，我覺得很好
I'm glad that you didn't feel empty.
不是空虛，真是太好了
I have never felt empty about anyone.
我從來不覺得誰很空虛
I have Branch Disease, and it's incurable.
那是一種叫分枝型梗塞的難治疾病
The blood streams in my head might get blocked or break anytime.
就算腦血管突然破裂或阻塞都不意外
I might die anytime.
無論何時死掉都不意外
I don't want you to feel empty.
我不想讓津輕小姐覺得空虛
I want you to feel happy.
我想讓津輕小姐覺得開心
Thank you very much.
謝謝
I want you to feel the same.
我對你也是相同想法
I will walk you home.
我送你回去
Murozono.
室園小姐
Do you know where Ken went?
你知道研先生去哪裡了嗎？
-No. -OK.
-不知道 -這樣啊…
Hey.
那個…
Huh?
嗯？
Did you encourage Ken to go on the radio to get away from Tsugumi?
你讓研去上廣播節目 是為了拆散他跟津輕小姐嗎？
If so, it's not like you.
如果是這樣，就太不像你的作風了
Murozono.
室園小姐…
Don't bother. You don't know anything.
明明什麼都不知道 就別想這些多餘的事了
Call me Mikoto.
叫我美琴啊…
TOKYO MUSASHI BROADCASTING AMAKUSA
（東京武藏廣播局 天草先生）
Hi. This is Amakusa.
你好，我是天草
Hi, Amakusa.
那個…天草先生
Will you stop Ken
那個…能請你…
from going on the radio?
別讓研先生繼續上廣播節目了嗎？
What are you talking about?
現在怎麼還說這個啊？
Come with him if you are worried about him.
如果你擔心的話，就直接來現場看啊
He seems to be full of life.
看看神采奕奕的研先生
It's almost three o'clock.
馬上就要三點了
Let's call SNACK MAN and the monster.
來呼喚點心男跟怪物吧
Where are they today?
今天在哪裡呢？
Hi. I am Junpei Amakusa.
好的，我是天草純平
Hi. I am Frankenstein.
好的，我是科學怪人
We are now visiting a kindergarten.
今天我們來到某所幼稚園
We got a message from a lady in here. Let's go.
這裡有投稿給我們的聽眾 趕快來看看吧
OK.
是
-Hello.
-午安
Did you send him a message?
您就是投稿給我們的母親嗎？
Yes.
是的
May I ask what message it was?
您想傳達什麼訊息給怪人先生呢？
Yes. My son came home from kindergarten
是的，其實我兒子從幼稚園回來
and listened to Franken talk on the radio.
就在聽怪人先生的廣播節目
Then he suddenly said that
結果
A monster?
怪物？
Do you mean your cute son is being called monster?
是您這位可愛的兒子 被人叫做怪物嗎？
Yes.
是的
He has an artificial leg.
其實我兒子
It doesn't mean that he is bullied,
所以就算不是帶有惡意的刻意霸凌
but the other children just call him a monster.
還是會被其他同學說成是怪物
When he was listening to the radio,
但這孩子聽了廣播以後
he told me that this monster is working hard, too.
就發現還有其他怪物先生正在努力
I see.
原來如此
So, I thought that he would try to run a race
所以如果…
if Franken rooted for him.
這孩子或許就願意做
My son has never run a race because he is scared of running.
以前從來不敢做的賽跑遊戲
So, I sent you a message.
雖然很任性，但還是投稿到貴節目了
I see.
這樣啊
What do you think?
怎麼樣，怪人？
What is a race?
賽跑遊戲是什麼？
It's to run with other people with all your might.
賽跑遊戲就是跟其他人
-I see. -It is to run
-是 -以終點為目標
as fast as you can to the goal.
盡全力奔跑
I see.
好
Will you run with me?
要和我一起跑嗎？
I have never run a race.
我也沒賽跑過
Won't you try with me?
要不要一起加油試試看？
He nodded his head.
少年點了點頭
Let's make a race.
那麼就來賽跑吧
I asked the other children to join.
我們也請了其他同學一起來幫忙
Come on.
來吧
OK. Stop here.
好了，停下，停下來
Don't push.
別推…
This boy is going to run a race for the first time in front of his mom.
在母親的面前
Before that, please check out the traffic information.
接下來請在路況報導後繼續收聽
Hey, do you feel jealous of the monster or Amakusa?
我說，你在嫉妒怪物嗎？
No.
我才沒有呢
They are ready to race.
賽跑的準備完成了
The boy is at the starting line,
少年站在起跑線
so are the other runners.
其他跑者也站在起跑線上
Now, the boy will race with Franken.
接下來怪人也會跟著少年一起開跑
-Are you ready, boy and Franken? -Yes.
-少年跟怪人都準備好了嗎？ -是的
How about you, boy?
這位少年呢？
Yes.
是
I'm sure he can do it.
似乎會好好努力
On your marks.
那麼，各就各位
Get set. Go!
預備…
The children started running. How about the boy?
其他跑者馬上就跑掉了，少年呢？
Come on!
加油！
He started running.
非常努力地起跑了
He fell down.
少年跌倒了
You can do it.
請加油
I was alone in the forest.
我一直獨自待在森林裡
I lived by myself without seeing anyone.
沒見過任何人，一直獨自生活
Then I heard a story about monsters on the radio.
就在這時，廣播傳來了怪物的故事
I was surprised to find out there were many monsters in the world.
我發現世界上原來還有其他怪物
But it was a sports event broadcast.
但那根本就是運動比賽直播
The man who was called a monster was a really great player.
被叫做怪物的人
A monster is a strong human.
怪物
People don't call you a monster if you are not strong.
若不堅強的話，就不會被叫做怪物
Please be a monster.
也請你變成怪物吧
Be a monster and make your mom happy.
變成怪物，讓媽媽開心吧
I will run with you.
我也會一起加油的
Let's do it together.
讓我們一起加油吧
Let's make her happy together.
一起讓大家開心吧
Go for it.
加油
Monster!
怪物！
Go for it!
加油啊！
This is complex.
真複雜啊
-Go for it.
-加油
-Hold the tape.
-稻庭學長，快就位 -是
You are almost there.
只差一點了
You did it.
你真了不起
I did it.
我辦到了
You did it!
太好了！
You did it.
太好了
-I did it!
-太好了！ -我辦到了
You did it.
辦到了呢
I did it.
辦到了
-Yes! You did it. -Good job!
-辦到了 -辦到了…
You worked hard today.
今天真是辛苦了呢
It was very touching.
錄到非常感人的內容呢
Thank you.
謝謝
Let's eat. Franken, please eat.
快吃吧，怪人也快吃吧
-Thank you.
-我開動了
Everyone did so well. I was so moved.
大家都做得很棒，我好感動
The boy, Franken, Amakusa, you all did well.
無論是少年、怪人還是天草
However, you are not suited for my radio program.
但是啊…我的節目不需要這種東西
It doesn't have to be wonderful and touching.
無論是那些美好或是感動
Radio should reflect the everyday life of the listeners.
廣播就是應該要貼近聽眾的日常生活
-Everyone has their everyday life. -I know.
無論是什麼人都要過日常生活啊
If radio gets too extreme,
要是在廣播節目 太過追求偏激的內容
it will confuse the everyday life of the listeners.
會打亂一邊工作 一邊聽廣播的人們的生活
No matter how tough or sad life is for the listeners,
我啊，無論發生多痛苦 或是傷心的事情
the radio should always keep a plain routine.
只有在廣播節目裡 我盡量分享最無聊的日常
It doesn't make you want to stop what you're doing to listen
懂嗎？雖然不會讓人停下來聽
but it gives people comfort.
但只要播放著，就覺得安心
That's what I want for my radio program.
我是在這信念之下才開這個節目的
But actually, many listeners like to know about the everyday life of Franken.
但實際上，怪人的日常生活 讓很多人都很開心
That's a fake life.
但那都是虛假的日常啊
It's all set up.
是被捏造出來的日常吧？
You whip up their emotions
煽動聽眾的情感
and do anything, just like TV shows, to make it fun for the moment.
根本就跟電視或綜藝節目一樣
I will decide if my program is fun or not.
我的節目有不有趣，由我來決定
What you do makes me feel empty.
你們的所作所為
I feel so empty.
空虛的不得了！
Hey, you.
你啊
Show yourself if you want to go on the radio.
既然上了我的廣播節目 就露出真面目吧
Franken?
什麼怪人啊？
I don't want cheap tricks in my program.
既然是我的節目 我就不會認同這種姑且的謊言
-Please wait. -What do you want?
-請等一下 -你到底又有何打算？
Are you looking for attention by being the girlfriend of a monster?
想被說成是怪物的戀人 被世人阿諛奉承嗎？
She doesn't have anything to do with this.
不，這跟她沒關係
Really? Is she just having fun?
沒關係？意思是說毫無關係 只是單純找樂子嗎？
I doubt if she is really sick.
說生了重病，也不知道是真是假
You're rude to her.
-十勝先生，你太失禮了 -你才失禮！
I have been working hard to establish my program.
跟我一手構築的節目道歉！
You just want to be popular. Shame on you!
你們全部都只是想引人注意而已
Ken.
深志先生…
What are you doing? Are you hiding something?
你鬼鬼祟祟的在做什麼？ 你藏了什麼嗎？
I'm sorry.
對不起…
I am afraid to be with you.
我害怕跟津輕小姐待在一起
I am your biggest fan.
我是你的頭號粉絲
Don't make any contact with Franken.
別再靠近怪人了
I encouraged him to go on the radio to keep him away from you.
我是為了拆散你跟津輕小姐 才讓你上廣播的
Show who you really are in front of everyone.
在大家面前露出真面目吧
I won't do anything.
我什麼都不會做的